<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-09T23:50:35+05:30</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your Site Title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Mapping the Conceptual Landscape: Why Definitional Space Matters for Automated Cell Biology</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/1_life_definitions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping the Conceptual Landscape: Why Definitional Space Matters for Automated Cell Biology" /><published>2025-06-09T15:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-06-09T15:30:00+05:30</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/1_life_definitions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/1_life_definitions/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="mapping-the-conceptual-landscape-why-definitional-space-matters-for-automated-cell-biology">Mapping the Conceptual Landscape: Why Definitional Space Matters for Automated Cell Biology</h1>

<h2 id="brief-context">Brief context</h2>
<p>This is a commentary on the paper I stumbled across in the QBio topic on arXiv. It was the only article there when I checked, and addresses one of the central problems in automating cell biology.</p>

<p><strong>Paper</strong>: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15849">What Lives? A meta-analysis of diverse opinions on the definition of life</a></p>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>One of the central questions in automating cell biology research is the question - to what end? What is the utility of the automatic research? What are the objectives towards which the entity that is pursuing understanding is geared towards, what are their goals? Often this has a utilitarian angle to it - such as prevention of disease or to live longer, but there are also enough examples of goals towards the understanding of the true nature of reality, especially of living systems. As living systems span across the domains of reality we have constructed, from thermodynamic, to ecological to abstract information kinds, anything we can usually think of can be applied to cells in some way and with the cell as a locus of understanding, can be explored further.</p>

<p>So this idea can often be summarized as the question - what is life? Such a question triggers the expression of the understanding of the various perspectives that exists amongst the practitioners of science.</p>

<h2 id="the-machines-approach-to-understanding-life">The Machine’s Approach to Understanding Life</h2>

<p>So, when you have a machine that has scientific cognition, and if it were to ask what is life, how might it approach that problem? It surely must construct what we can call the definitional space, as the authors of this paper have done, and attempt to gather or categorize empirical evidence that support one or many of the paradigms the authors have outlined. Of course, how the machine might choose to answer the question of what is life, on its own, or whether if we can create such a machine, which can choose of its own a path to pursue is a huge question that I do not have the answer to at this moment.</p>

<p>Perhaps the machine is always coded towards at least some initial condition, and perhaps that might be towards some utilitarian or purist-reality-truth-seeking goals, or towards a paradigm, and shifts towards something else, or has these list of paradigms/concepts to start with, and moves onto discovering, engineering new concepts we didn’t think of, which we might use as a toolbox for our utilitarian goals… you see things can get a bit tricky.</p>

<h2 id="a-methodology-for-mapping-conceptual-evolution">A Methodology for Mapping Conceptual Evolution</h2>

<p>One thing that’s particularly nice about this paper is that they established this methodology for creating definitional space. That’s a real merit of this work. This methodology can aid in keeping track of the definitional space temporally, with periodically running such analysis, and can also be applicable across diverse granularities. We could imagine tracking how our understanding of fundamental concepts evolves over time, or applying similar approaches to more specific biological questions - what defines a stem cell, what constitutes cellular intelligence, or how we understand disease states.</p>

<h2 id="definitional-space-as-conceptual-scaffolding">Definitional Space as Conceptual Scaffolding</h2>

<p>But it is nevertheless good to have this definitional space, if we are to think that we are going to be handholding machines as they learn scientific cognition. And it would be really good measure to be able to see if they fit within a framework their understanding so that we can understand whether we are on the same page, at least in the initial days. The risk of not having this shared conceptual framework would be in the creation of narrow perspective, biased systems, which we expend a lot of resources into, without actually making progress.</p>

<p>The definitional space serves as conceptual scaffolding - a way to establish common ground between human and machine understanding while providing a structured starting point for scientific inquiry. Without this framework, we risk building sophisticated but fundamentally limited systems that operate within narrow paradigms we haven’t even explicitly recognized.</p>

<h2 id="beyond-human-limitations">Beyond Human Limitations</h2>

<p>What makes this particularly interesting is that while the paper performs a survey of philosophers and scientists, there’s a fundamental limitation in that these thinkers are not pure experimentalists. However, machines can also perform experiments of their own - grow samples, apply the scientific method, test hypotheses, and have almost incomparable capability in hardware, software and wetware. So they have some advantages in the conceptual space that could potentially expand our definitional landscape in ways we haven’t yet imagined.</p>

<p>The definitional space, then, becomes both our starting point and our method for ensuring that as machines develop their own scientific cognition, we maintain enough shared understanding to recognize when they’re making genuine progress versus when they’re pursuing narrow, unproductive paths.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mapping the Conceptual Landscape: Why Definitional Space Matters for Automated Cell Biology]]></summary></entry></feed>